Chambrun mss., 1864-1901 LMC 2850
Lilly Library
Chambrun mss.
1864-1901
2014
Lilly Library
Charles-Adolphe de Pineton, Marquis de Chambrun
LMC 2850
5 Boxes
The Chambrun mss. consists of correspondence and political papers of French lawyer Charles-Adolphe de Pinetone, Marquis de Chambrun.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
Charles-Adolphe de Pineton, Marquis de Chambrun (1831-1891) was a French lawyer who served as the unofficial French representative in the United States during the Civil War. He married Marthe-Helene de Corcelles, a direct descendant of Marquis de Lafayette, after she was introduced by Alexis de Tocqueville. The family and their circle of friends were liberals in the age of Napoleon III. Adolphe's political leanings and pamphleteering against Napoleon III and the French state forced him out of France. Despite not speaking any English, he left for America to establish a law practice. Ignoring Chambrun's politics, Edouard Drouyan, the French Minister of Foreign Affairs, gave him an informal diplomatic role in the United States: to observe the progress of the American Civil War, as well as Napoleon III's scheme that had put Maximilian I on the throne in Mexico -- a move highly unpopular in the United States.
Arrangement
This collection is organized by I. Correspondence and II. Political-Related Papers
Scope and Content Note
The archive includes correspondence and political-related papers from 1864-1901. Acquired: 2014 Collection Size: 5 Boxes
Acquisition Information
Purchase: 2014
Civil War; French; United States --History --Civil War, 1861-1865 --Regimental histories.; Lawyers--France; Lawyers--France--Biography; Diplomats; Diplomats--France--Correspondence; Diplomats--France--Biography; Diplomats--United States; Diplomats--United States--Biography; de Pineton, Charles-Adolphe, Marquis de Chambrun; de Tocqueville, Alexis, 1805-1859; Napoleon III, Emperor of the French, 1808-1873; Chambrun, Marie Henriette Hélène Marthe Tircuy de Corcelle, marquise de, 1832-1902; Maximilian, Emperor of Mexico, 1832-1867
- I. Correspondence
  - Group 1 (Box 1)
  - Group 2 (Box 1)
  - Group 3 Part I – Family Tree (Box 1)
  - Group 3 Part I – 1875 (Box 1)
  - Group 3 Part I – Letters 1875-76 (Box 1)
  - Group 3 Part I, (4 folders) (Box 1)
  - Group 3 Part I – 1885, (2 folders) (Box 1)
  - Group 3 Part II – 1886 (Box 1)
  - Group 3 Part II – 1887 (Box 1)
  - Group 3 Part II – 1888, (4 folders) (Box 2)
  - Group 4, Part I, (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Group 4, Part II, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Group 4, Part III, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Group 4, Part IV, (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Group 5 Part I, (7 folders) (Box 3)
  - Group 6 Part I, (7 folders) (Box 3)
- II. Political-Related Papers
  - Group 1, Part I, (4 folders) (Box 3)
  - Group 1, Part II, (3 folders) (Box 3)
  - Group 2, Part I, (5 folders) (Box 4)
  - Group 2, Part II, (4 folders) (Box 4)
  - Group 2, Part III, (5 folders) (Box 4)
  - Group 3, Part I, (5 folders) (Box 4)
  - Group 3, Part II, (4 folders) (Box 4)
  - Group 4, Part I, (3 folders) (Box 5)
  - Book: Impressions of Lincoln and the Civil War (Box 5)
  - Book: Un Francais Chez Les Lincoln (Box 5)